Guide to the Anne Tjomsland papers, [ca. 1838-1966]
Tjomsland, Anne papers,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Anne Tjomsland papers, [ca. 1838-1966]
2924
Anne, Tjomsland, 1880-1968.
4.2 cubic ft.
Correspondence, photographs, publication reprints, patient record notes, schoolwork, and manuscripts.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes correspondence, photographs, publication reprints, patient record notes, schoolwork, and manuscripts. Materials relating to her service in WWI, such as her application, contract, and petitions for veteran benefits, are also included. Tjomsland's correspondence covers both her daily and professional life, including her work as a translator and writer. Also includes her correspondence with Morris Bishop, author of "A History of Cornell," about her experience as a student in Burt Green Wilder's class.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Dr. Anne Tjomsland (Cornell University B.A. 1911, M.D. 1914) worked at Bellevue Hospital in New York City before serving as a contract surgeon for the U.S. Army in Vichy, France during World War I. She wrote about her experiences with the Bellevue Hospital medical unit in her book "Bellevue in France: Anecdotal History of Base Hospital No. 1." When she returned to the U.S. Tjomsland continued to practice medicine as a general practitioner and anesthesiologist. She also began pursuing a Ph. D. in history at Columbia University, stopping a few credits short. Tjomsland continued writing, both fiction and non-fiction, as well translating Norwegian medical histories and Icelandic mythology. In 1951, Cornell University Library issued her translation of "The Saga of Hrafn Sveinbjarnarson: The Life of an Icelandic Physician of the Thirteenth Century" as Islandica Volume 35.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes correspondence, photographs, publication reprints, patient record notes, schoolwork, and manuscripts. Materials relating to her service in WWI, such as her application, contract, and petitions for veteran benefits, are also included. Tjomsland's correspondence covers both her daily and professional life, including her work as a translator and writer. Also includes her correspondence with Morris Bishop, author of "A History of Cornell," about her experience as a student in Burt Green Wilder's class.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Tjomsland, Anne, 1880-1968.; Bishop, Morris.; Waller, Erik.; Thorek, Max.; Reichborn-Kjennerud, Ingjald.; Hermannsson, Halldor.; Fahraeus, Robin.; Falkberget, Johan.; Cornell University -- Alumni and alumnae.; Cornell University -- Students.; World War (1914-1918)
Subjects:
Women college students.; Authors.; Medicine.; Physicians.; Women physicians.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Medical care -- France.; Authors; Medicine; Physicians; Women physicians
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Under the HIPAA Privacy Rule, all individually identifiable health information in patients' medical records in Box 4 are restricted.
RELATED MATERIALS
Related collections: Mary Merritt Crawford and Family Papers, #41-5-619
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence, 1838-1966
Boxes 1-2
Series II. World War I Related Materials, 1914-1963
Box 3
Series III. Writing and Translations, 1910-1963
Box 3
Series IV. Schooling Materials, 1891-1949
Box 3
Series V. Research Materials, 1935-1959
Boxes 4-6
Series VI. Photographs, 1904-1956
Box 4
Series VII. Assorted Materials, 1904-1961
Box 4
CONTAINER LIST
- Correspondence, 1838-1966
  Contains personal and professional correspondence.
  - Assorted Correspondence, 1838-1966
    Arranged chronologically.
    - Blank postcards, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Postcards, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence and documents from Norway, 1838-1902 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1872, 1880-1889 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1908-1916 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1916-1919 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1921-1922 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Assorted postcards, 1924, 1935, 1938, 1942, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, 1924-1925 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Correspondence, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Correspondence, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Correspondence, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Assorted postcards, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Holiday cards, 1950-1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Assorted postcards, 1960-1965 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Holiday cards, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Subject Correspondence, 1919-1965
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Et. Petit correspondence, 1923-1933, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Henry E. Sigerist correspondence, 1933-1957 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Fredrik Gron correspondence, 1934-1937, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Nordisk Tidende Newspaper correspondence, 1934-1939 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Ingjald Reichborn-Kjennerud correspondence, 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Nordisk Tidende Newspaper correspondence, 1935-1951 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Halldor Hermannsson correspondence, 1936-1954 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Erik Waller correspondence, 1937, 1948-1955 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Valentine Colonna correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Sigrid Undset correspondence, 1939-1949 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Dittrick correspondence, 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Correspondence on Reichborn-Kjennerud obituary and pamphlets, 1946-1950 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Page Cooper correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Genevieve Miller correspondence, 1947-1963 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Petra Jaabek correspondence, 1947-1954 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Junius Bird correspondence, 1947-01-1948-10 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - George Strong correspondence, 1947-11-1949-10 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - John La Monte, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Ellen H. Ringer, 1948, 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Max Thorek correspondence, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Austin Evans correspondence, 1948-02-1949-05 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Amy Grace Mekeel correspondence, 1949, 1957-1965 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Temkin Correspondence, 1949-1960 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Emma and Inger Munch correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Chr. M. Spilling correspondence, 1950-1954 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Ciba - The History of the White Potato, National Potato Council correspondence, 1951, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - History of Medicine by Robin Fahraeus correspondence, 1951-1962 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Egill Snorrason correspondence, 1952-1964 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Pentothal postcards, 1956-1957, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Odd Helland correspondence, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - NSF Medical translation inquiries, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - G. Natrud correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Curt Proskauer correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Iago Galdston correspondence, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Felix Marti-Ibanez correspondence, 1957-1964 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - D.H. Daugherty, American Council of Learned Societies correspondence, 1957-06-1958-11 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Erik J. Friis, Robert Hunter related correspondence, 1958-1965 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Accident related correspondence, 1959-1962 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Morris Bishop correspondence, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Family Correspondence, 1914-1966
    - Family correspondence, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Family correspondence, 1914-1915, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Family correspondence, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Family correspondence, 1935-1938 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Family correspondence, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Family correspondence, 1954-1959 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Family correspondence, 1960-1966 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- World War I Related Materials, 1914-1963
  Contains materials related to Tjomsland's service as a contract surgeon in World War I.
  - Vichy photographs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Red Cross Cases - France, 1914-1919 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Singing in Vichy writing, 1917-1919 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - WWI soldier photographs, 1917-1919 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - WWI soldier photographs, 1917-1919 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - WWI U.S. Army application and related materials, 1917-07-1919-05 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Passport and application, 1918-02 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - U.S. Army technician appointment, 1918-02-1919-03 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - U.S. Treasury Department Patriotic Cooperation citation, 1945-12-31 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Veteran pension petition correspondence, 1956-06-1958-05 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Social Security benefits petition correspondence, 1958-05-1958-07, 1963-05, 1965-03 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Veterans' Exemption from Real Property Taxes application, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - U.S. Army contract, 1918-12-04 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - U.S. Army French transport form, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 65)
- Writing and Translations, 1910-1963
  Contains fiction, non-fiction, and translated manuscripts, including her history of the Bellevue Hospital medical unit in France during World War I.
  - Bellevue in France, 1915-1943
    - Bellevue Hospital photographs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Bellevue Hospital newspaper clippings, 1915-1926 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Bellevue Hospital article, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Bellevue in France book reviews, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Bellevue in France book notice, 1942-05-23 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Other Writing and Translations, 1910-1963
    Arranged chronologically, if no date arranged alphabetically.
    - Assorted poetry and notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Assorted poetry and notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Assorted writing and notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Another Kind of Place, Undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - The Captain of the Men of Death, Undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Hermann Von Helmholtz, Undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - The Incoming Tide, Undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Jan Fearnley's Flower-piece, Undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Karin, Undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Off the Norwegian Coast, Undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - The Saga of Hrafn Sveinbjarnarson translation, Undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Ships that List, Undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Tug, Undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - A Visit to Stratford-on-Avon, Undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Assorted writing and notes, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - The Glory of Opportunity series, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - The Life Clinic, 1914-1915 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Daily journal entries, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Hospital stay notes, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Robin Fahraeus articles, 1956-1957, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Bergman Ole Johnsen Jamt translation, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Robin Fahraeus book translation, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - It Can't Be Done, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - The Bear Hunters in Bjollelfa translation, 1959-10, 1961-04 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Don Felipe and Covarrubias history, 1963-09 (Box 3, Folder 66)
- Schooling Materials, 1891-1949
  Contains mainly coursework from Columbia University, as well as work prior to college.
  - Columbia University papers and notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Columbia University papers and notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Columbia University History of Italian Medicine, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Columbia University History 167, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Columbia University Philosophy 165-166, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - School notebooks, 1891-1893, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Central High School, 1904-05-27 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Neurology drawings and notes, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Columbia University History 235-236, 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Columbia University History of Science notebook, 1935-1939 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Columbia University Latin notes, 1936-1939 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Columbia University History 132, 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Columbia University History 25-26: Intro to the History of Science, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Columbia University History 171, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Columbia University History 201, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Columbia University Latin America, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Columbia University History, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Columbia University papers and notes, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Columbia University papers and notes, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Columbia University History 115-116, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Columbia University Presidential Inauguration program, 1948-10-12 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Eisenhower, Dwight D.
  - Columbia University transcripts, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Research Materials, 1935-1959
  - Bibliographic index cards, Undated (Box 6)
  - Bibliographic index cards, Undated (Box 7)
  - Horse index cards, Undated (Box 4)
  - Personal notebooks, Undated (Box 4)
    Includes notes on Vichy, anesthesia, Falkberget, and address books. Some notes are in shorthand.
  - Victor Robinson materials, 1935-1948 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Frederick Barry materials, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Application for Public Health Service Research Grant, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Photographs, 1904-1956
  - Assorted photographs, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Assorted photographs, Undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Europe trip photographs, Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Maranon photographs, Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Max Thorek photographs, Undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Anne Tjomsland photographs, Undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Venice photographs, Undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Erik Waller photographs, Undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Anne Tjomsland photographs, 1904, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Canoe trip photographs, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Norway photographs, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Mexico photographs, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Spain photographs, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Norway photographs, 1946-1947, 1954, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Carl Burdick photograph, 1917-1919 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Assorted Materials, 1916-1961
  - Patient records A-Z, Undated (Box 4)
    Under the HIPAA Privacy Rule, all individually identifiable health information in patients' medical records in Box 4 are restricted.
  - Resume and professional history notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Dinner at 501 and France photographs, assorted painting reprints, Undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Birth certificate statement, 1916-07 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Passports, 1924-04, 1935-08, 1954-08 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - English Setter dogs information, 1926, 1944-1947, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - New York City lease, 1929-1932 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Spain trip materials, 1935-1936 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Ole Tjomsland materials, 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Europe trip materials, 1956-08 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - 10th Congresso Internacional de Historia de la Medicina related materials, 1935-09-1936-05 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Hans Tjomsland notebooks, 1903-1928 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Unprocessed material, Date Unknown (Box 5)